<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Reply to a paper written by one of the six-clerks, intituled, An answer to a printed paper of the under-clerks in Chancery, intituled, Reasons to be offered, &amp;c.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 30 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91658</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1053</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E826_17</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207733</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866769</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866769</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119055</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91658)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119055)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 125:E826[17])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Reply to a paper written by one of the six-clerks, intituled, An answer to a printed paper of the under-clerks in Chancery, intituled, Reasons to be offered, &amp;c.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>14, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>A reply to:  A Printed paper of some of the under-clerks in Chancery intituled Reasons to be offered.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Feb: 1654".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Court of Chancery --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Printed paper of some of the under-clerks in Chancery intituled Reasons to be offered.</term>
               <term>Courts --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119055:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A REPLY TO A PAPER Written by one of the Six CLERKS, INTITULED, <hi>An Anſwer to a Printed Paper of the under-Clerks in Chancery,</hi> INTITULED, <hi>Reaſons to be offered,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>THE Reſpondent or Author of the Paper doth well to Intitle himſelf <hi>A Lover of Truth and Juſtice,</hi> elſe no man by his Writing could ever have thought him ſo. And where he conjectures the Reaſons to be framed <hi>by ſome under-Clerks in Chancery,</hi> he may poſſibly be ſo farre in the right, but not a word further: And for the ſatisfaction he deſires, <hi>who will own it,</hi> he may pleaſe to underſtand that the Clerks of the Court do generally own it, and many of them have ſo expreſt themſelves unto me, and for the truth of the matter, no man need to doubt it; for if it might be put into a way of Examination, it would be made appear upon the Oathes of 100 ſeverall perſons, and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:119055:2"/>if the Author thinks himſelf, and the reſt of his brethren ſcandalized with matter of truth, I cannot help it.</p>
            <p>And the Author having finiſhed his Prologue (inſtead of giving an Anſwer to the Reaſons) fals a railing at the Clerks for ſaying <hi>their Allowances are too ſmall, and cals them ſherks for that they ſhare with the ſix Clerks in the Fees which the Clients pay.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In Vindication of whoſe Reputation, although I forbear to ſay, that the ſix Clerks have firſt ſherked upon the Clerks, yet I ſhall truly inform the Reader how they have uſed the Clerks, and not the Clerks alone, but even the Lord Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector himſelf, and all the people of the Nation, and leave it to others to give their actions a name according as they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve. For anciently when the buſineſſe of the Court was but little, and the ſix Clerks were not only nominall, but reall Attorneys, adviſing and directing Clients, and laying out and disburſing money for them, and thereby adventu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the loſſe thereof, and with their own hands writing all the ſpeciall buſineſſe of the Court (wherein any Clerkſhip was required) and had but one or two young Clerks apiece, to write and copy things of an ordinary and eaſie nature, even then the ſame young Clerks (their meniall ſervants) had all the Fees which the ſix Clerks of late allowed to the practizing Clerks, and had alſo their Diet, Chamber-rent, Paper, Ink, Parchment and Candles, Blank-writs of all ſorts, ſecond Copies, renued Writs, and Copies of Decrees and Diſmiſſions, and the whole Fees of many Writs, ſome of which the ſix Clerks themſelves afterwards took from the Clerks, and others they ſuffered to be taken away by Paten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tees, as making Subpenas, ingroſſing of Grants and Leaſes to the great Seal, and the like, which the ſix Clerks oppoſed not, it trenching upon the Clerks only. And when the ſix Clerks ceaſed to act for the Clients as Attornies, making it their chief imployment to keep Books of Entries, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to exact their pretended Fees, all the care and burden of Cauſes being caſt upon the Clerks, and they compelled to disburſe all monies to be laid out for Clients, and very often with their own mony to pay the Clients Fees (which grew
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:119055:2"/>due for their own labour) to the ſix Clerks, which they never received again from the Clients, and undergo all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hazards and loſſes. And when all the aforeſaid allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances were likewiſe withheld from them, and the benefit of divers Writs gone as aforeſaid, it may be truly ſaid that there was a neceſſity laid upon the Clerks to withhold a greater part of the Fees, which the Clients paid, then the ſix Clerks would ſeem willing to allow them, and this they might lawfully do without violation of the Laws of God or man, for I finde no text of Scripture that erects ſuch Officers as the ſix Clerks to live upon the peoples purſes, without any care or regard of, or ability to do them ſervice in their Cauſes, nor is there any Statute or other Law that creates them ſave only their illegall Parent granted in the time of Monopolies by the late King <hi>Charles,</hi> but there are ſeverall Acts of Parliament prohibiting the buying and ſelling of Offices: And I likewiſe finde a Text of Scripture where the righteous God (taking upon himſelf the buſineſſe of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation) promiſeth his people to ſend them <hi>Judges as at the firſt and Officers as at the beginning.</hi> From whence it may be concluded, that Officers and others in Publique imployment had need ſometimes to be reformed and brought to their Primitive conſtitution. And if the ſix Clerks were ſtill ſo continued and made to become work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Attorneys as at the firſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ao</hi> 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi> Ri. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> they were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed from three to ſix.</note> and ſo many more added un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them and made Attorneys likewiſe, as are neceſſary for diſpatch of the buſineſſe of the Court, I think no man would deſire to remove them out of ſuch their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per imployment, or to receive one penny of their Fees. But they have not only thus abuſed the Clerks, but have in a much higher nature abuſed the Lord Protector, and all the people of the Nation, Witneſſe their receiving very large Fees for inrolling all ſuch Grants and Pardons and other things as paſſe the Great Seal, and never inrolling or eſtreating many of them, whereby the Lord Protector and Commonwealth are very much abuſed, and the Rents and Reſervations upon them (for want of ſending Eſtreats into the Exchequer) never appear, whereby they may be
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119055:3"/>demanded or levied as they ought to be. And the people are greatly abuſed, not only their Eſtates, but their Lives being in danger, for want of inrolling the Grants and Pardons, there having been few or none inrolled for theſe fourteen years laſt paſt. And the Warrants and Privy Seals for paſſing them are ſo ill kept, that many of them within theſe nine or ten years laſt are quite rotten, not to be read again, ſo that now its impoſſible ever to have them inrolled: and the truth hereof would appear, were the Clerks appointed for keeping the Records examined upon Oath, and ſearch made at the Hamper Office what Patents have paſſed within theſe fourteen years laſt paſt, and then ſee in the Chappell of the Rols and Exchequer how many of the Rols are ſent to the Chappell of the Rols, or Eſtreat into the Exchequer. And now what name theſe doings and actions of the ſix Clerks ſhall have, I leave to the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to judge. But I am ſure, that which the Author of the Pamphlet cals ſherking in the Clerks, is but the recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of leſſe then one half of the wages due for their own labours, which ſome of the greateſt and moſt wiſe of the late ſix Clerks have acknowledged to be due, and of right belonging to them. For I remember when I waited upon one of the ſix Clerks, ſome of the younger ſort of them propoſing Rules of practice to tye the Clerks to a more ſtrict Accompt, I heard that grave and wiſe Gentleman M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Saunders</hi> (ſometime one of the <hi>ſix Clerks</hi>) expreſſe himſelf to this effect, <hi>viz. Let them alone, they do the Work that we ought to do, they disburſe their own mony, and ſave us from disburſing ours, they bring us a great profit, and run all the hazard, and if they do receive one half of the Fees paid by the Clients, it is no more then is neceſſary to maintain them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and families.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And I appeal to all indifferent men, whether if one of the ſix Clerks receive clearly into his own Purſe 1500 or 1600<hi rend="sup">l</hi> 
               <hi>per Annum</hi> or more, by the labour of the Clerks in his Office, which are ſeventeen or eighteen perſons, (as by their own Certificate to the Committee for Regulation of the Chancery appears,) Whether thoſe ſeventeen or eight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119055:3"/>perſons ſhould not receive amongſt them all to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain their families, ſo much as one ſix Clerk had to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain his: The ſix Clerk in the mean time, having no hazard, but receives his money ready down from the Clerks whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they receive it or no, and the Clerks adventuring that which they pay down to the ſix Clerks, their own Fees, and all other disburſements which many times are loſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And as touching the Eſtates which the Pamphlet mentions to be gained by the practiſing Clerks out of their former allowan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces;</hi> I ſay, That although the Clerks did at the time he ſpeaks of, ſhare with the ſix Clerks, and receive as much of the Fees paid by the Clyents, as they have done at any time ſince; Yet he cannot name above two perſons, that ever gained any conſiderable Eſtate by that imploiment<note n="*" place="margin">E. R. H. P.</note>. And for any others, the Eſtates they have gotten are but ſmall, and much inferiour to the Eſtates that many other induſtrious men have acquired in imploiments much inferiour to theirs. But it may be truly obſerved, that the ſmall Eſtates gained by the Clerks have proſpered better then the large Eſtates gotten by the ſix Clerks; For memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry hath ſcarce recorded, that ever an Eſtate gotten by a ſix Clerk remained to his poſterity one age after his death.</p>
            <p>In the next place the Author of the Pamphet ſeems much to undervalue the Clerks pains, ſaying, <hi>They take pains to part ſtakes with the ſix Clerks, and that the ſervants of the Clerks take more pains then the Clerks themſelves.</hi> But here (as in all the reſt of the Pamphlet) although he ſtyles him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf <hi>a Lover of the Truth,</hi> yet he loves not to ſpeak the truth; Witneſſe his miſ-reciting the Ordinance, and men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioning <hi>thirteen Groats allowed to the intended Attourneys;</hi> where it is but ten Groats, and his miſ-repeating the Reaſons likewiſe; and where the Reaſons ſay, the Clerk might juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly receive part of the Fees which the ſix Clerks claimed, he repeats it, <hi>That they might eaſily do it.</hi> And I would know of the Author, Where (in the Paper which he cals <hi>the Clerks paper</hi>) he findes any acknowledgement, <hi>That the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119055:4"/>Fees allowed by the Ordinate to the intended Attourneys, are as great as the Fees allowed to the Attourneys of other Courts?</hi> I am ſure I can finde no ſuch thing therein, but his paper is ſtuft with nothing but untruths: <hi>And touching the Clerks pains,</hi> I would know of him, Who are the Perſons that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect and adviſe all the Clyents of the Court in their Cauſes, and draw all the ſpecial Writs, Commiſſions, Decrees, Diſmiſſions, and other things? Surely he will not ſay, that either the ſix Clerks, or the Servants to the practiſing Clerks do, or can do any of theſe things. And whether theſe things can be done without much care and pains, I leave it to any other (except the Author) to judge: As alſo, Whether the caſe be the ſame twixt the ſix Clerks and Clerks, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Clerks and their menial ſervants, or between a man and his ſervant whom he teaches and inſtructs in an imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and maintains with meat, drink, lodging, and other neceſſaries? The ſix Clerks being none of them bred in the imployment, and ſo know nothing of it, when they purchaſe their Offices, and what knowledge they after attain to in the imployment they learn from the Clerks, and not the Clerks from them.</p>
            <p>And where <hi>any untruth is laid down as a foundation</hi> in the Reaſons (as the Author would inſinuate) I cannot ſee; I hope he doth not mean that the Clerks ſay untruly, in ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>they were compelled to pay the ſix Clerks the Fees due from the Clyents, and never received them again:</hi> For the Author by his long experience cannot but know, that he hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled the Clerks to pay him ſome hundreds of pounds, that they never received again from the Clyents: And every Clerk that hath had any conſiderable practice, if examined upon his Oath, would depoſe, that the ſix Clerks have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted from him ſome ſcores of pounds that he never did or could receive again from the Clyents. And although I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the Author be a better Divine then a Clerk or Lawyer, yet he can hardly finde it reſolved amongſt all the Caſuiſts, that the Clerks are bound in conſcience to pay their Clyents Fees, out of their own purſes to the ſix Clerks, although they never received them of the Clyent, or that it is <hi>fraud
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:119055:4"/>or unjuſt covetouſneſſe,</hi> if they (being unjuſtly compelled ſo to do at one time) re-imburſe themſelves at another time. As <hi>for the pains pretended to be taken by the ſix Clerks,</hi> I leave to all the Clyents in <hi>England</hi> to judge what it is.</p>
            <p>And ſeeing the Author by his paper gives occaſion to lay forth their nakedneſſe, which I never found the Clerks to have done, I will with moderation (not with railing, as he doth) tell you what they do; They only keep Books, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they enter the names of the Clyents for their better recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Fees, to which none have acceſſe but themſelves; for as ſoon as they go from their Offices in the vacation, they either take thoſe Books along with them, or lock them up, ſo as no man hath uſe thereof, or benefit thereby, but them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, ſo that this labour might be very well ſpared, and the Cauſe would proceed ſomewhat the faſter. They likewiſe attend in Court, and reade Clyents Books, but the Clerk muſt attend likewiſe to give him the Book or Writing that he is to reade: And might not this formality then be likewiſe ſpared? And were it not as little labour for the Clerk to reade them himſelf in Court, as to give them to the ſix Clerk to read?</p>
            <p>They alledge, <hi>Diſpatch of references,</hi> but they arc chiefly of their own occaſioning, and if they were able to give a preſent accompt to the Court of the courſe and practice of Court, and the proceedings in Cauſes as able Attourneys might do, the references would be ſpa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed, and the Court and Clyent much eaſed.</p>
            <p>The Author further ſaith, <hi>By the ſame Argument the Clerks would ſhare with the ſix Clerks in the Fees, ſo might a Plowman or Souldier claim as much as his Landlord or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander, and that the Clerks proceed unjuſtly in making their pains the rule of propriety, and not Law and Juſtice, and that they promiſed the ſix Clerks upon their Admittances to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with their Allowances, but never kept their words. And that they teach the Lord Protector, and the honourable Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee what Fees ſhould be paid; And that they go along with the Levelling Party, and are dangerous Perſons to be truſted,</hi> and divers ſuch like untrue and ſcandalous Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertions.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:119055:5"/>
In Anſwer whereunto, I deſire the Reader to peruſe the later end of my Paper, entituled, <hi>A Diſcovery of certain grievances in the Court of Chancery,</hi> &amp;c. where he will finde a full Anſwer to theſe ſleight Objections. Whereunto I add further, That the Clerks may well make the pains to be taken for Clyents the beſt Rule of Propriety to entitle them to Fees ſutable to their pains and ſervice, eſpecially where the matter and Fees are under conſideration of Parliament to be reformed and appointed to every one according to deſert, and a <hi>quantum meruit</hi> lies at Common Law for recovery of meet ſatisfaction for pains taken; Therefore the Author of the Pamphlet doth well to confeſſe ingeniouſly, that he and the reſt of his Brethren had need of a further help then a <hi>quantum meruit</hi> to recover their Fees, and therefore may well diſclaim to have <hi>the pains taken for Clyents to be the Rule of Propriety.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſurely the Clerks would have been too blame, if they had been altogether ſilent, when they found that ſome of the Fees intended to them are ſo ſmall, that the Parch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment will coſt them more then they are to receive for the ſame when it is written: With this, that they no wayes went about <hi>to teach the Lord Protector, or the honourable Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee What Fees are to be paid,</hi> but humbly offered their Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and left it to their conſideration in an humble and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate way, not making their Reaſons publick, as the Author of the Pamphlet hath done them, and his own Paper, by ſelling them publickly to the Stationers, I ſuppoſe, partly to make profit to himſelf, but chiefly to aſperſe and calumni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate the Clerks; for had I not found the Pamphlet ſo publick at every Stationers ſhop, I had ſpared this labour, though now in reſpect of my former relation to them, I thought my ſelf by way of gratitude bound to vindicate them, I finding them ſilent herein. Neither do the Clerks, as the Author of the Pamphlet falſly inſinuates, <hi>Runne with the levelling Party;</hi> for I never underſtood that it was a <hi>levelling princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> for an Apprentice when he hath paid his money, and ſerved his Apprentiſhip, to deſire to be free of his Trade: Or for a Student of the Univerſity or Inns of Court, after
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:119055:5"/>he hath continued a convenient time, and done his Exerciſe, to deſire to take Degrees, or be called to the Barre: And if this be levelling, all the Attourneys of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Pleas and Upper-Bench have been <hi>Levellers</hi> for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ages laſt paſt; for that Attourneys Clerks of thoſe Courts, after they have ſerved a convenient time, and fitted themſelvs for that imploiment, have never been denied to be admitted Attourneys.</p>
            <p>And ſurely the Gentleman diſcovers a high Principle of Tyranny, that would have ſo many Free-men of <hi>England,</hi> men of Repute and Fortune, Maſters of Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to be under a Yoke of Servitude, and be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted as their <hi>menial Servants</hi> all the dayes of their lives; And he is no leſſe injurious and unconſcionable to <hi>appropriate the practiſing Clerks Fees to the ſix Clerks,</hi> that ſo the Clerks might be at their Will and Pleaſure only; For what greater Tyranny and Oppreſſion can there be in the world, then when a man hath given a ſumme of Money to be bred up in an Imployment, and then ſerved in it all his life, perhaps twenty or thirty years, to have a ſtranger illegally to ſtep over him into an Office, and without any cauſe hold him to any un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſcionable Terms and Conditions by promiſe or other Engagements, and to exact and extort the Fees (paid by the Clyents) from the Clerk, and compell him to pay the ſame out of his own Purſe, though he never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it himſelf, or elſe turn him out of that imployment, wherein he was bred, and upon which he depends for his ſubſiſtence?</p>
            <p>And as touching the <hi>Petition annexed to his Paper,</hi> although many of the perſons mentioned to be Petition<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, diſown the ſame, and divers names are put thereto of men who never were heard of the be Clerks in the Office? yet I ſay, that the three pence <hi>per</hi> ſheet then deſired together with the profit of the <hi>Dedimus Poteſt.</hi> and ſuch other Fees, as they then received, did amount to as much as the whole Fees now allowed by the Table of Fees annexed to <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:119055:6"/>Ordinance, and yet not more then was neceſſary to ſupport themſelves and Families.</p>
            <p>And whereas the Author of the Pamphlet would inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate into the Souldiery, to have the ſix Clerks lookt upon <hi>as the Officers of the Army, and the Clerks as the common Souldiers;</hi> and thereupon concludes, <hi>That it is as unjuſt for the Clerks to deſire their Fees, as for the common Souldier to deſire their Commanders pay:</hi> He therein miſtakes the caſe: For the ſix Clerks are but At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tourneys, and the Attourneys of every Court, are, or ſhould be as the common Souldiers in an Army (the men on whoſe ſhoulders the moſt hard and laborious work of the Court doth lie.) And as well he might ſay, That if an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my conſiſted of five thouſand common Souldiers, and there were a neceſſity in reſpect of ſome ſervice to be done to increaſe theſe five thouſand to twenty thouſand, that theſe five thouſand ſhould monopolize the pay of the other fifteen thouſand, and put on them the whole burthen of the ſervice, and allow them what pay they pleaſed, and disband them at pleaſure: And the Indenture being tripartite, I have ſealed him a third part thereof; Whereby he may ſee, That the caſe he puts concerning others, is their own, which is that they being in the nature of common Souldiers, <hi>viz.</hi> Attour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys of a Court of Juſtice, deſire and receive Officers pay, whereby their profit (as it was formerly) was not only much greater then the Fees acquired by moſt Councel which are before them in place, but as great as the Maſter of the Rolls, or any other Judges in <hi>England,</hi> even the Lords Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners themſelves (as I conceive) ſo that I may truly ſay to him, <hi>Mutato nemine de te fabula narratur.</hi> But I have ſpent more time then need in clearing this, for that every man knows, That an Army cannot admit of any ſuch idle, uſeleſs, and exorbitant Officers, as are the ſix Clerks, and ſome other pretended Officers in Chancery, who were origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally but <hi>Clerici ſecundae formae ſcribentes in rotulis prepr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is manibus.</hi> But they have received Officers pay ſo long, that they would now fain be Commanders, and forget
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:119055:6"/>that they are but Attourneys in the nature of common ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers.</p>
            <p>And whereas the Author of the Pamphlet unworthily goes about to perſwade the People, That the Clerks have principles of fraud radicated in them, and are not fit to be truſted, I ſay, that if the Clerks did not perform the truſt repoſed in them, both to the Court and Clyent, better then the ſix Clerks performed their truſt, the buſineſſe of the Court would have been in farre worſe condition then now it is (although it be bad enough) for certainly all the care and faithfulneſs that hath been performed either towards the Court or the Suitors, as to the practical part thereof, hath been performed by the Clerks, and by none but the Clerks. As to inſtance in the paſſing of a Decree (being a thing of as great moment, as any thing in the Court betwixt party and party) the Clerks take much pains and care truly to collect and compoſe it out of the Pleadings and Orders of the Court, and then examine the ſame with the ſame Pleadings and Orders, wherein he often ſpends three, four or five dayes, and then preſents it to the ſix Clerk to be ſigned; who there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon certifies the Court that he hath examined it, and receives twenty ſhillings for the ſame, although in truth, he knows not one word that is contained in it; nor can moſt of the ſix Clerks ſay (if they ſpeak the truth) that ever they examined a Decree in their lives, nor if they ſhould examine them, do they know whether the ſame are done, as they ought to be, or not. And hereupon the Regiſter upon the Clerks credit, preſents it to be ſigned by the Lords Commiſſioners, ſo that there is no pains or care beſtowed about it, but what is done by the Clerk; nay I will boldly affirm, If the Clerks of the Court had been ſuch as the Author of the Pamphlet ſtyles them, it had been no hard matter for them (till of late that a greater care hath been taken by the Lords Commiſſioners) to have paſſed Decrees againſt any man in <hi>England</hi> for ten thouſand pound, there being no care taken what was preſented to the Lords Commiſſioners to be ſigned, but what was done by the Clerks: And as in Decrees, ſo I might
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:119055:7"/>inſtance likewiſe in almoſt every thing that is done in the Court.</p>
            <p>And I hope, if there be juſt cauſe (as certainly there is) to make ſixty or ſeventy Attourneys in the Court of Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery, every judicious man will think it reaſonable, that the Attourneys of the Court (now) ſhould have half ſo much allowed them for their Fees, as the Attourneys of the ſame Court had two hundred years ſince; carefull, laborious and able Attourneys, being men of ſo great truſt and abſolute neceſſity in every Court of Juſtice, that the buſineſs of the Court cannot be done without them.</p>
            <p>But as for ſuperintendent Officers, ſuch as are the ſix Clerks, chief Regiſter and chief Examiners, Subpena Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Although many think it to be an honour to a Court to have ſuch Officers in it, and therefore Propheſie that their removall will occaſion many inconveniencies and diſorders, yet I will tell them, that theſe and ſuch like Officers are the diſgrace and diſhonour of a Court of Juſtice: And the Chancery never was in ſo great Honour, as when there were none but working Attornies and Clerks, <hi>viz. (Clerici pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae &amp; ſecundae formae)</hi> every of which truly performed the work and labour for which they were ordained: Nor was the Court ever in ſuch diſhonour and ignominy, as it hath been ſince theſe Clerks became Officers. And give me leave (like a poor <hi>Micaia</hi>) to foretell, that there never will nor can be any effectuall Reformation, as long as there are ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perintendent Officers continued, between the Maſter of the Rols and the Clerks of the Court, (who diſpatch the Clients buſineſſe) to receive the greateſt part of the Fees which the Clients pay: For whatſoever Fees are allowed, whether it be the ſame in the Ordinance, or more or leſſe, if the Clerks receive the ſame to their own uſe, the buſineſſe will be well diſpatched, and the Records well kept; whereas if the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt part of the Fees (which are paid pending the ſuit) be given to Superintendent Officers, buſineſſe will never be well done. And the Rule obſerved in ancient time is very remarkable, where we may ſee how carefull and prudent
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:119055:7"/>men were, that Clients Cauſes ſhould not be obſtructed; for when the Maſter of the Rols was only a Miniſteriall Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer (<hi>viz.</hi> chief Clerk) and the ſix Attornies acted for Cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents in all reſpects as Clerks do now, the Maſter of the Rols received no Fees from any Clients pending the ſuit, but the Attornies who did the whole buſineſſe received the whole Fees due for the ſame to their own uſe. But at and after the hearing of the Cauſes, the Maſter of the Rols received Fees, <hi>viz.</hi> for every Decree and Diſmiſſion <hi>vjs</hi>—<hi>viijd</hi>, and for every Exemplification <hi>Vidimus</hi> and <hi>Conſtat,</hi> the like Fee.</p>
            <p>And no doubt this was ſo done that the Attornies might have no cauſe to neglect or delay the Clients Cauſes, which they would undoubtedly have done, if the Maſter of the Rols being the then chief Clerk had received the greateſt part of the Fees, due for their Labours; but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if he had compelled them to pay their Clients Fees out of their own Purſes, whether ever they received them of the Clients or not, as of late hath been practiſed; for 'tis impoſſible to make a Law to binde the Conſciences of men, with their own Money to pay other men the rewards and wages due for their own Labour. And (with ſorrow it is ſpoken) I am now become of the ſame opinion with thoſe (though I have formerly much oppoſed them) who think that a Court or Courts of Juſtice, or other thing that is of a publique, concernment to the Commonwealth, when the ſame hath proceeded in an irregular and diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly way, grievous to the people, without any through and full Reformation for the ſpace of eighty or an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years, that then it is altogether impoſſible to reform them: For they ſay (and I finde it too true) That in ſo long a continuance of time there will be ſo many men of quality and eſtate immediatly concerned, and ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others mediatly concerned upon the Accompt of friendſhip or other like accompt, that this of it ſelf will be a great Bullwork againſt an impartiall Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:119055:8"/>
I have heretofore anſwered this and the like Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and urged to the Objector thus, Why might not men of ability and integrity, and men no waies, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned neither immediatly nor mediatly, call every man one by one that hath any relation to a Court of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice before them and examine him, and alſo ſuch others as are fit to be examined, what Fees every man receives from the Clients, and what ſervice they perform for the ſame Fees, and whether, this be for the good and advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of Clients, and neceſſary to be done, or whether ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous and unneceſſary, and performed only for the Fees ſake, and not for any good it brings to the people. And by this narrow ſcrutiny it might be brought to ſuch a perfect and exact Reformation, that no man ſhould be continued to receive ten groats or ten pence from the Client, that could not give a good Accompt why he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives it, and that he performs ſome neceſſary ſervice for the Client, deſerving the ſame. But I do not ſee that this courſe is like to be taken; For they that are exalted and ſtand on the upper ground (becauſe they ſee more then I do) think they ſee all; whereas I, and others like me, that ſtand much below them, do ſee things which they by reaſon of their diſtance of place cannot ſee. Yet I hope and pray that I may ſee a reall Regulation and Reformation of the Court of Chancery, which if I do not ſee effected, I ſhall not yet ceaſe, (having little elſe to do) to tell the people of this Nation (and that more plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly then I have yet done) where the fault lies.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:119055:8"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
